# 今天是週末哦
It's weekend today.
# 去搞了一點小魚
I've fetched some small fish.
# 剛好加加餐 小孩子都回來啦
So we can have an extra dish. The kids are all back here.
# 那個放地籠 放地籠
Well, the trap, I've put the trap,
# 裝了一點魚回來
and have caught some fish.
# 這是螃蟹 這是石班魚
These are crabs, these are (freshwater) groupers,
# 這個是pa gong
and these are "pa gong" (untranslatable local carps).
# 家裡又沒有煤氣啦
We've run out of gas here again.
# 用這個柴火
I'm gonna use the firewood.
# 這個柴火不用錢的
The firewood is free of charge.
# 嗯 著啦
Um! It glows.
# 誒呀 這麼多水
Aya! It's so wet.
# 一吹就滅掉啦
The fire can't even stand a single blow of wind.
# 好 可以啦
Alright! Fine!
# 夠啦
It's enough.
# 家裡沒甚麼青菜 我去兄弟家搞點來
I don't have much veggies left here. So I'm gonna get some from my buddy's place.
# 拿這個筲箕來
I go with this sieve.
# 好多魚魚
A lot of fishy!
# 這個魚魚
These fishy
# 哪裡
Where?
# 跑啦
They've run away.
# 好多魚
A lot of fish
# 小小的 是不是
They're so tiny, aren't they?
# 哪裡 看到沒有
Where?
See?
# 是 好多這個魚魚 你不要抓
Yea! Here are a lot of fish. Don't try to catch them!
# 等掉溝裡面去喲
We might fall into the ditch otherwise.
# 刘星辰
Liu Xingchen!
# 不要下去啦
You're not going down!
# 很髒 有水
It's dirty, and it's wet!
# 去 到裡面摘菜 走
Let's go! We go inside for the veggies. C'mon!
# 刘楚萱
Liu Chuxuan!
# 衣服都被你撐爛啦
You're ruining your T-shirt!
# 刘星辰你不要下去啦
Liu Xingchen, you're not going down!
# 你看 兄弟家的老茄子
Look! My buddy's old eggplants,
# 又大又長
are all big and long.
# 我把它摘掉一點
Let me help him pick some,
# 幫它吃掉一點
and help him finish some.
# 哎呀 小狗你也來啦
Aya! Doggie, you're here too?
# 3個 夠啦 我看一下有沒有攀蒲
Three. It's enough. Let me see if there are any pumpkins.
# 搞兩個攀蒲回去 再搞點青椒
I'm gonna get a couple of pumpkins, and also some green peppers.
# 差不多就這樣啦
And I think that's it.
# 這裡面 前面好像有苦瓜哦
Here inside. There seems to be some bitter gourds in the front.
# 我來摘兩個
I'm gonna pick a couple of them.
# 這個
This one
# 好 這三個
Alright! These three
# 好靚哦
Beautiful!
# 三個
So three
# 還有其它的 再看一下其它的有沒有
There are something more. Let's see if there's anything else.
# 哎呀 這裡有一個
Aya! Here's one.
# 這裡有一個小南瓜
Here's a small pumpkin.
# 很小的 看到沒有
It's really small, see?
# 這個南瓜
This pumpkin,
# 特別小
is exceptionally small.
# 一個就夠啦 我吃一餐就可以啦
One is enough. It's only for one meal.
# 搞一點青椒 對面有青椒哦
Let me pick some green peppers. There are green peppers on the other side.
# 這 這裡還有青椒
Here, here are some green peppers too.
# 這 這青椒
These, these green peppers,
# 摘點來配菜
let me pick some as side ingredients.
# 這裡有一個
Here's one.
# 就沒啦
Just one?
# 誒喲 一條狗在這裡
Eyo! A dog is here!
# 嗯 都爛啦 這個有點 爛啦
Um! It's rotten. This is a bit, rotten.
# 夠啦 你看
Enough! Look!
# 都是兄弟家的
These are all from my buddy.
# 天天都有蔬菜吃 (註︰這個不想直譯，直譯感覺好像只是說一個飲食習慣而已，所以寫得更明白一點)
I'm never short of veggies.
# 先煎
First let's fry,
# 先煎點魚
fry some fish.
# 先把大的先下鍋
I put the big ones into the wok first,
# 小的慢慢來
followed by the small ones.
# 這是小的
These are small.
# 小的等下一鍋就煎啦
I'll fry the small ones all together in a while.
# 你看 這個 可以啦
Look! This is, alright now.
# 這個煙囱
This is a chimney.
# 太大煙啦
It's too smoky.
# 來啊
C'mon!
# 現在煙都沒的出
Now the smoke is not coming out.
# 你看 搞了這幾個 搞到現在天都黑啦
Look! So I'm done with these dishes. It's already dark now.
# 好 還有一個
Ya! One more dish
# (刘星辰，我的瓶子被狗咬壞了怎麼辦) (註︰這個沒有原字幕，但太清楚了，我想一拼翻譯)
(Liu Xingchen! The dog is chewing my bottle. What should I do?)
# 還有一個
One more
(Liu Xingchen! The dog is chewing my bottle. What should I do?)
# (刘星辰，我的瓶子被狗咬壞了怎麼辦)
# 被你端走啦
You've taken it away.
(Liu Xingchen! The dog is chewing my bottle. What should I do?)
# (刘星辰，我的瓶子被狗咬壞了怎麼辦)
# 可以準備吃飯啦
Alright! Let's get ready for dinner.
# 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
So the video ends here.
# 開始吃飯啦
We're gonna have our dinner.
# 開飯啦 開飯啦
Meal time, meal time!
# 哦 我要可樂
Oh! I want coke!
# 你要可樂哇
You want coke, right?
# 好可以啦 不要喝多啦
Alright, enough! Not too much
# 不能一起喝的
Don't share!